L. L. Waters papers, 1921-1994 C138
Indiana University Archives
L. L. Waters papers
1921-1994
1940-1994
Indiana University Archives
Waters, L. L.
C138
12 cubic feet 12 boxes
L.L. Waters was a professor of Transportation and Business History in the Indiana University School of Business from 1948 until his retirement in 1978. Waters was a recognized authority on transportation and business. The Waters papers include a large amount of correspondence, material related to conferences and professional organizations, teaching files, manuscripts, and published works.
Access Restrictions
Files containing student recommendations are closed to researchers at this time.
Advance notice required for access.
Biographical Note
Lawrence Leslie Waters was born in Axtell, Kansas, on February 3, 1913. He earned a B.S. from Central Missouri State in 1935, and his Ph.D. from the University of Illinois in 1939. Waters taught in the School of Business at the University of Kansas from 1939 to 1948, where he won an Excellence in Teaching award in 1947.
In 1948, Waters came to Indiana University as a professor of Transportation and Business History in the School of Business. He remained with the school until his retirement in 1978. Waters won Excellence in Teaching awards in the Business School in 1971, 1974, and 1976. He was the coordinator of the European Productivity Agency program at Indiana University from 1955 to 1960 and played a role in the Indiana University International Business Forum from 1980 to 1994. From 1961 to 1966, Waters was the IU administrator of the Ford Foundation program for the improvement of teachers.
Dr. Waters was a recognized authority on transportation and business. He authored or co-authored over a dozen books in these fields and wrote numerous articles, speeches and book reviews. He edited innumerable books and articles, and served on the editorial boards of several publishers and journals.
Waters belonged to or held high offices in many professional organizations. Especially noteworthy was his service with the American Society of Traffic and Transportation, for which he served as a Director, President, and Chairman of the Board; his work with the Military Airlift Committee of the National Defense Transportation Association (Advisory Board, 1973-1984); and finally, his service to the Transportation Council of the United States Department of Commerce (member of Executive Committee, 1957-1960). Waters served as a consultant for corporations and for governmental units at the state and national level. He was on the board of directors of many companies, including Yellow Freight and Baldwin & Lyons, Inc.
The honors Waters received during the course of his long career include: the Salzberg Honorary Medallion Award, presented by Syracuse University (1985); the National Defense Transportation Association's President's Award for Contributions to National Defense (1984); the Joseph C. Schleen Award for Excellence in Traffic and Transportation, presented by the American Society of Traffic and Transportation (1978); Distinguished Business Scholar, 1976-1977, by Beta Gamma Sigma; and the Distinguished Service Award in Transportation and Public Utilities, presented by the American Economic Association (co-winner, 1976). Waters was Indiana's Transportation Man of the Year in 1974. In 1979, the Indiana Transportation Conference was renamed the L. L. Waters Transportation Conference. Waters was awarded honorary doctorates by the University of Ghent (1979) and Indiana University (1987).
Waters married Mary Louise Harrison in 1937. They had three children: Robert Lawrence, Linda Jean, and Donna Louise. Waters died on September 8, 2012 at the age of 99 in Bloomington.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into five series: Correspondence, Teaching, Professional organizations and conferences, Consulting, and Scholarship and publications.
Scope and Content Note
The L.L. Waters papers span the years 1921-1994 and are organized into five series: Correspondence, Teaching, Professional organizations and conferences, Consulting, and Scholarship and publications.
The first series, Correspondence, is further organized into two subseries: General correspondence and Administrative and interdepartmental correspondence. With correspondence spanning the period from 1939 to 1994, the General correspondence subseries is arranged chronologically and within folders alphabetically by the correspondent's surname. The correspondence in this series reflects Waters' active professional life and includes notes from many professional contacts pertaining to transportation-related issues, research, conferences, and publications. Most of the correspondence is with Waters' colleagues outside of Indiana University, but not exclusively. Frequent correspondents include William Buchanan, general manager of the Louisville, New Albany & Corydon Railroad Company, as well as other leaders in transportation companies. Other frequent correspondents include fellow faculty in business and related fields throughout the country, particularly colleagues from the University of Kansas, Lawrence, such as Ethan Allen and Frank Stockton. The Administrative and interdepartmental correspondence subseries (1950-1994) is arranged alphabetically by folder heading. This subseries contains a large amount of interdepartmental correspondence spanning the period from 1950 to 1977. Correspondence relating to Waters duties as coordinator of the European Productivity Agency program at IU can be found within these files. Items with student grades and recommendations have been removed. A small sample of recommendation letters have been retained but are restricted at this time and have been physically placed at the end of the collection.
Teaching is a brief series with materials dating from 1936-1971. Items such as exam questions, reading lists, bibliographies and early student evaluations of Waters' teaching can be found in this series. Files are arranged alphabetically by folder heading. A small sample of recommendation letters have been retained but are restricted at this time and have been physically placed at the end of the collection.
The Professional organizations and conferences series spans the years 1949-1994. It is arranged alphabetically by organization or conference name. The bulk of the material in this series pertains to conferences, and includes submitted papers, conference schedules, and correspondence regarding conference planning. Materials related to the Indiana University International Business Forum makes up a sizable portion of the subseries. Correspondence, newsletters, meeting minutes and other materials relating to the American Society of Traffic and Transportation and the Midwest Business Administration Association can also be located in this series.
The Consulting series is dated 1948-1987 and is arranged alphabetically by organization name. Organizations represented include the National Defense Transportation Association, the University of Tennessee, and the World Bank. Included are reports by Waters and his colleagues, correspondence, and research material.
The final series, Scholarship and publications, is further organized into three subseries: Research material and correspondence related to publications, Manuscripts, and Publications. The Research material and correspondence subseries is dated 1921-1994, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1940s. It primarily contains correspondence and news clippings related to research projects such as the Santa Fe Railroad and research for the book Energy to Move. The second subseries, Manuscripts, is arranged alphabetically by folder heading and contains typescripts of articles, papers, reviews, and speeches by Waters from the years 1934-1991. This subseries also contains the manuscripts of two books, Investments and Transportation in Indiana. In addition, there is one folder of typed and handwritten papers written by Waters as a student. The Publications subseries spans the period from 1936 to 1991. It is arranged alphabetically by type of publication. Included are articles and monographs, book reviews, and books, including Waters' Energy to Move and Steel Rails to Santa Fe, as well as both his master's and Ph.D. theses. There are also bound issues of Your Business from the Bureau of Business Research at the University of Kansas, which Waters directed from 1939-1948. Some issues contain articles by Waters, but many do not. The books within the publications subseries are arranged chronologically.
Separated Material
Six photographs of students involved with the European Productivity Agency have been transferred to the Archives Photograph collection. Contact the Photographs Curator for more information.
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 94/066
Provenance
Transferred to the University Archives in 1994. Deed of gift received in 1997.
Appraisal
Items with individual student grades have been removed and destroyed.
Letters of recommendation were sampled and the remainder destroyed.
Transportation --Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington.; Transportation --Research.; Business teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Indiana University. School of Business -- Faculty -- Archives; Waters, L. L. -- Archives; Waters, L. L. -- Correspondence
- Correspondence, 1939-1994; undated (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1939-1994 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1949 (Box 1)
      - A-Z (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
      - A-Z (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
      - A-K (Box 1)
      - L-Z (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
      - A-F (Box 1)
      - G-M (Box 1)
      - N-Z (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
      - A-G (Box 1)
      - H-P (Box 1)
      - R-Z (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
      - A-I (Box 1)
      - J-Z (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
      - A-G (Box 1)
      - H-Q (Box 1)
      - R-Z (Box 1)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence and Papers from Sabbatical (Box 2)
        - A-P (Box 2)
        - R-Z (Box 2)
    - 1956 (Box 2)
      - A-B (Box 2)
      - C-E (Box 2)
      - F-H (Box 2)
      - I-Q (Box 2)
      - R-Z (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
      - A-B (Box 2)
      - C-E (Box 2)
      - F-H (Box 2)
      - I-L (Box 2)
      - M-S (Box 2)
      - T-Z (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
      - A-C (Box 2)
      - D-H (Box 2)
      - I-M (Box 2)
      - Mc-R (Box 2)
      - S-Z (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
      - A-C (Box 2)
      - D-H (Box 2)
      - I-M (Box 2)
      - Mc-R (Box 2)
      - S-Z (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
      - A-C (Box 2)
      - D-H (Box 2)
      - I-M (Box 2)
      - Mc-R (Box 2)
      - S-Z (Box 2)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
      - A-C (Box 2)
      - D-H (Box 2)
      - I-M (Box 2)
      - Mc-R (Box 2)
      - S-Z (Box 2)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence related to Rose Morgan Professorship at University of Kansas (Box 2)
    - 1962 (Box 3)
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-H (Box 3)
      - I-M (Box 3)
      - Mc-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1963 (Box 3)
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-H (Box 3)
      - I-M (Box 3)
      - Mc-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1964 (Box 3)
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-H (Box 3)
      - I-M (Box 3)
      - Mc-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence related to around-the-world trip 1964 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (Box 3)
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-H (Box 3)
      - I-M (Box 3)
      - Mc-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1977 (Box 3)
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-H (Box 3)
      - I-M (Box 3)
      - Mc-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-H (Box 3)
      - I-M (Box 3)
      - Mc-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-H (Box 3)
      - I-M (Box 3)
      - Mc-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1970 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1971 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1975 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1976 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1977 (Box 4)
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-H (Box 4)
      - I-M (Box 4)
      - Mc-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
    - 1978-1980 (Box 4)
      - A (Box 4)
      - B (Box 4)
      - C (Box 4)
      - D (Box 4)
      - E (Box 4)
      - F (Box 4)
      - G (Box 4)
      - H (Box 4)
      - I (Box 4)
      - J (Box 4)
      - K (Box 4)
      - L (Box 4)
      - M (Box 5)
      - Mc (Box 5)
      - N (Box 5)
      - O (Box 5)
      - P (Box 5)
      - Q-R (Box 5)
      - S (Box 5)
      - T (Box 5)
      - U (Box 5)
      - V (Box 5)
      - W (Box 5)
      - X, Y, Z (Box 5)
    - 1981-1994 (Box 5)
      - A (Box 5)
      - B, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - C (Box 5)
      - D (Box 5)
      - E (Box 5)
      - F (Box 5)
      - G (Box 5)
      - H (Box 5)
      - I (Box 5)
      - J (Box 5)
      - K (Box 5)
      - L (Box 5)
      - M (Box 5)
      - Mc (Box 5)
      - N (Box 5)
      - O (Box 5)
      - P (Box 5)
      - R (Box 5)
      - S (Box 6)
      - T (Box 6)
      - U (Box 6)
      - V (Box 6)
      - W (Box 6)
      - X, Y, Z (Box 6)
    - Annual Christmas Letters, 1976-1991 (Box 6)
    - Author Unknown, undated (Box 6)
      General
      (probably late 1970s)
  - Administrative and interdepartmental correspondence, 1950-1994; undated (Box 6)
    - 1907 Fund (later UPS Fund), 1971-1990 (Box 6)
    - Committee on Names, 1978-1994 (Box 6)
    - Committee on Special Ranks/Distinguished Professorships, 1966-1987 (Box 6)
    - Concerned Titled Professors (Distinguished and Named Chair Professors), 1979-1994 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and material related to the dedication of the new Business School, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
    - European Productivity Agency, 1956-1965 (Box 6)
      - Biographies of students, 1956-1972 (Box 6)
        (6 photos removed)
      - Correspondence, 1958-1965 (Box 6)
        - General, 1962-1965 (Box 6)
        - Participants, 1958-1960 (Box 6)
        - Students, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Faculty Annual Report, 1950-1977 (Box 6)
    - Ford Foundation Pakistan Project, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
    - Hartley, Joseph P, 1959-1977 (Box 6)
    - Herman B Wells Program for Outstanding Young Scholars, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Institute for Advanced Study, 1993-1994 (Box 6)
    - Interdepartmental Correspondence, 1950-1977 (Box 6)
      (Restricted materials removed)
      - 1950 (Box 6)
      - 1951 (Box 6)
      - 1952 (Box 6)
      - 1953 (Box 6)
      - 1954 (Box 6)
      - 1955 (Box 6)
      - 1956 (Box 7)
      - 1957 (Box 7)
      - 1958 (Box 7)
      - 1959 (Box 7)
      - 1960 (Box 7)
      - 1961 (Box 7)
      - 1962 (Box 7)
      - 1963 (Box 7)
      - 1964 (Box 7)
      - 1965 (Box 7)
      - 1966 (Box 7)
      - 1967 (Box 7)
      - 1968 (Box 7)
      - 1969 (Box 7)
      - 1970 (Box 7)
      - 1971 (Box 7)
      - 1972 (Box 7)
      - 1973 (Box 7)
      - 1974 (Box 7)
      - 1975 (Box 7)
      - 1976 (Box 7)
      - 1977 (Box 7)
    - International Council, 1990-1993 (Box 7)
      - 1990 (Box 7)
      - 1991 (Box 7)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 7)
    - Proposal to Study the Management of NASA, undated (Box 7)
    - Recommendations for students and related material, 1977-1993 (Box 7)
      (Restricted Materials Removed)
      - A-K, 1977-1993 (Box 7)
      - M-Z, 1977-1993 (Box 7)
    - Satellite Communications, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Search Committee for a new dean of the Music School, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Smerk, George M., 1964-1979; undated (Box 7)
    - Wilson, George, 1957-1978 (Box 7)
      - General, 1957-1994 (Box 7)
      - Special professorship, 1966-1978 (Box 7)
- Teaching, 1936-1971; undated (Box 7)
  - Exams for H-100, undated (Box 7)
  - Exams for T-502, undated (Box 7)
  - Student evaluations of Waters' teaching, University of Kansas, 1936 (Box 7)
  - Teaching materials (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1944-1971 (Box 7)
    - T-507, 1968-1970; undated (Box 7)
- Professional organizations and conferences, 1949-1994 (Box 8)
  - American Society of Traffic and Transportation, 1949-1971 (Box 8)
    - 1949-1958 (Box 8)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 8)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 8)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - 1965 (Box 8)
    - 1966 (Box 8)
    - 1967 (Box 8)
    - 1968, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1969, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 8)
  - Indiana Transportation Conferencebulk, 1966-1977; 1977 (Box 8)
  - Instituto De Estudios Superiores De Administracion (1975) and National Accounting and Finance Council Convention (1975), 1975-1976 (Box 8)
  - International Conference on Prices and Productivity, 1972 (Box 8)
  - International Conference on Business (1976), 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - Papers, 1976 (Box 8)
  - International Business Forum (1981), correspondencebulk, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
  - International Business Conference (1981) submitted papers (Box 9)
  - International Business Forum, correspondence and related material, 1982-1994 (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1983 (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1984; (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1985 (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1987 (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1989; (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1991 (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1992 (Box 9)
    - meeting, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Future of IBF, 1992-1993 (Box 9)
  - International Conference on the Baltic (1991), correspondence and related material, 1990-1991 (Box 9)
  - Midwest Business Administration Association (1989), correspondence and material related to 25th Anniversary of organization (including accounts of its history), 1965-1989 (Box 9)
  - Salzberg Medallion, correspondence and related papers, 1984-1994 (Box 9)
- Consulting, 1949-1987; undated (Box 9)
  - Bureau of Business Research Publications, 1955; 1964 (Box 9)
    - Feasibility of Port Development at Michigan City, 1964 (Box 9)
    - Indiana's Economic Resources and Potential, 1955 (Box 9)
  - Grocery Manufacturers of America, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
  - Handley Administration, economic consulting work (includes newspaper clippings), 1958-1959 (Box 9)
  - Indiana State Planning Agency, 1977-1978 (Box 9)
  - Indiana Toll Road Commission, 1954 (Box 9)
  - Kansas City Consulting, 1966-1968 (Box 9)
  - National Defense Transportation Association, Military Airlift Committee, 1971-1983 (Box 9)
    - 1971-1974 (Box 9)
    - 1975 (Box 9)
    - 1976 (Box 9)
    - 1977 (Box 9)
    - 1978 (Box 10)
    - 1979 (Box 10)
    - 1980 (Box 10)
    - 1981 (Box 10)
    - 1982, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1983 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Consulting Reports, 1948-1965; undated (Box 10)
  - National Research Council, Transportation Research Board, 1980-1982; (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - University of Tennessee, Review of Transportation Program, 1982-1987 (Box 10)
    - 1982, (4 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 10)
  - Testimony of L. L. Waters, 1960-1972; undated; (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Transportation Council, U.S. Dept. of Commerce, undated (Box 10)
  - World Bank, 1978-1980 (Box 10)
    - Indonesia and the Philippines, 1979-1980 (Box 10)
    - Tunisia, 1978-1980 (Box 10)
- Scholarship and publications, 1921-1993; undated (Box 11)
  - Research material and correspondence related to publications, 1921-1993; undated (Box 11)
    - Clippings and notes about British Railways (notebook), 1954-1955; undated (Box 11)
    - Santa Fe Railroad correspondence, 1930-1944 (Box 11)
      - 1930, 1941 (Box 11)
        (Includes a map of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway System, 1930)
      - 1942 (Box 11)
      - 1943-1944 (Box 11)
    - Seward and Company, clippings and notes, 1921; undated (Box 11)
    - Texas Gas Transmission Corporation, 1978-1993 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, (especially related to book Energy to Move), 1978-1993 (Box 11)
        - 1978-1984 (Box 11)
        - 1985-1993 (Box 11)
      - Research material/documents, 1978-1985; (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Tucker Corporation, newspaper clippings, 1947-1950 (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts, 1934-1991; undated (Box 11)
    - Articles, papers, reviews, speeches, (organized by alphabetically by title), 1941-1991 (Box 11)
      - A-C, 1941-1991 (Box 11)
      - D-F, 1941-1991 (Box 11)
      - G-K, 1941-1991 (Box 11)
      - L-O, 1941-1991 (Box 11)
      - P-R, 1941-1991 (Box 11)
      - S-Z, 1941-1991 (Box 11)
    - Investments, 1947 (Box 11)
      - Introduction through chapter XII, 1947 (Box 11)
      - Chapters XIII-XVIII, 1947 (Box 11)
    - Term papers, 1934-1947 (Box 11)
    - Transportation in Indiana (manuscript), written with Charles Thomas Moore, 1956; undated (Box 11)
    - Untitled and undated manuscripts (Box 11)
  - Publications, 1936-1991 (Box 11)
    - Articles and monographs, 1940-1987 (Box 11)
      - A-M, 1940-1987 (Box 11)
      - N-Z, 1940-1987 (Box 11)
    - Book reviews, 1965-1983 (Box 11)
    - Sampling of Letters of Recommendation and Related Materials (Box 11)
      (Restricted)
    - Books, 1936-1991 (Box 12)
    - Waters, L. L.Recent Forest Conservation Activities of the Federal Government. Master's thesis, University of Illinois, 1936 (Box 12)
    - Waters, L. L.State Obstructions to Interstate Trade with Reference to Use Taxes and Liquor Control. Ph.D. dissertation, University of Illinois, 1939 (Box 12)
      (An abstract of the dissertation, in pamphlet form, accompanies the diss.)
    - Waters, L. L., Use Taxes and Their Legal and Economic Background. Kansas Studies in Business, no. 19. Lawrence, KS: University of Kansas Bureau of Business Research, 1940 (Box 12)
    - Your Business. Bulletin of Business Research, University of Kansas. vol 1.1 through vol. 2.10, (November 15, 1946 - June 15, 1948); (Bound) (Box 12)
    - Waters, L. L., Steel Rails to Santa Fe. Lawrence, KS: University of Kansas Press, 1950 (Box 12)
    - Waters, L. L.; Broehl, Wayne G., Jr.; Spencer, Charles H.; and Powell, Ray M. Administering the Going Concern. Edgewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1962 (Box 12)
    - Waters, L. L., Energy to Move. Owensboro, KY: Texas Gas Transmission Corporation, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Filgas, James F and Waters, L. L. Yellow in Motion. Overland Park, KS: Yellow Freight System, Inc., 1987 (Box 12)
    - Waters, L. L .,Will You Be Our Speaker? Privately published by L. L. Waters, 1991 (Box 12)